Biophysical Society records
Biophysical Society records
1955-2009
1955 2010
Coll014
Biophysical Society
116 boxes (50.5 linear feet)
116 boxes
50.5 linear feet
The collection documents the origins of the Biophysical Society, its growth, and its work in promoting biophysical education and research. Materials include correspondence, legal documents, constitutions and by-laws, meeting minutes, budget and financial reports, administrative files, conference programs and catalogs, presentation and research abstracts, membership directories, publication files, publications and journals, copies of the Society's newsletter, and committee and sub-group files. One series is dedicated to interaction with two affiliated professional organizations, the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (FASEB) and the International Union of Pure and Applied Biophysics (IUPAB).
University of Maryland, Baltimore County Albin O. Kuhn Library and Gallery UMBC 1000 Hilltop Circle Baltimore, MD 21250 410-455-2353 speccoll@umbc.edu
This collection of records of the Biophysical Society, 1955 – 2003, documents the early origins of the Society, its growth in membership as well as committees and areas of interest, and its work in promoting both education and research in the field of biophysics. These records have been arranged into five primary series that reflect the basic organization of the Society. Each of the series: Officers and Executive Committee, Meetings, Committees, Publications, and Affiliated Societies contain the documents of committees, boards, and individuals responsible for the workings of a particular area of the Society’s activity.
Series one contains the files of the Biophysical Society’s Officers and Executive Committee. The series is subdivided into five sub-series: Association Legal Documents, Correspondence, Executive Board Meetings, Finances, and Administrative Files. The first sub-series, Association Legal Documents, begins with the 1958 Articles of Incorporation and also contains constitutions and by-laws from the 1950s and 60s. This series does contain some correspondence relating to the constitutions and by-laws. The correspondence sub-series dates from 1955 – 1998. Correspondence covers a wide range of topics, which the Executive Committee and Officers dealt with; it also contains numerous emails. The Executive Board Meetings sub-series contains material addressing Society issues from the 1950s through 2002. One meeting of interest is the 1972 meeting, which discussed a lawsuit against the director of the National Institute of Health (NIH) and the Secretary of the United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. The lawsuit was brought by a caucus of women biophysicists in order to address discrimination on public advisory boards. The 1973 meeting contains a discussion of the Equal Rights Amendment, which was tabled for the 1974 meeting. The Finances sub-series deals with the Society’s various accounts as well as budget reports and financial statements. Several Treasurer reports from the 1990s are also included. The Administrative Files, covering mostly the 1960s and 70s, includes a discussion of creating an archive for the Society. The Society Archivist, Max Lauffer, wrote a general history of the first 25 years of the Society, which is included in these Administrative Files. General rosters and committee rosters cover the time span from 1959 – 1996.
The second series contains the Society’s Meeting records and is divided into two sub-series: Annual Meetings and Miscellaneous Conferences and Meetings. The first sub-series, Annual Meetings, is comprised of files for the Society’s annual meetings from 1956 – 2000. Included are organizational materials including files of the program committee and the local arrangements committee along with printed programs, abstracts, reports, minutes, correspondence and catalogues. This sub-series also includes numerous copies of meeting information and calls for papers as well as correspondence relating to the annual meetings. One item of interest is located in Box 9 Folder 43 with the 1981 meeting information and call for papers. The item consists of a series of photographs of the Society’s founders taken at the 1981 annual meeting. The second sub-series, Miscellaneous Conferences and Meetings, is comprised of files for individual conferences and meetings such as the Second, Tenth, Eleventh, and Fourteenth International Biophysical Congresses.
Series three, Committees, is comprised of files from a variety of the Society’s committees, and is divided into seven sub-series. Files for both standing committees and ad hoc committees provide a view of the varied interests and activities of the organization. Files span the years 1956 – 1998 and include correspondence, reports, memos, minutes, agendas, and directories. The seven sub-series are as follows: Awards Committee, Educational Affairs Committee, Innovative Technology Fund Advisory Committee (ITFAC), Joint Steering Committee, Membership Committee, Nominating Committee, and Miscellaneous Committees. One item of interest is the records of the Joint Steering Committee, which was charged with lobbying Congress on behalf of the Society and biophysicists in general. Files include a 1991 discussion of the Space station debate as well as a discussion of genetic engineering. The Membership Committee files contain printed directories from 1957 – 1999 with only a few years missing. Membership Committee correspondence also contains a list of biophysicists to contact in order to see who would be interested in forming a society. One item of interest with the Nominating Committee is a 1997 committee handbook.
The fourth series, Publications, is made up of three sub-series: Biophysical Journal, Newsletter, and Publications Committee. The first sub-series contains correspondence with Rockefeller University Press, the publisher, as well as financial information from RUP. This sub-series also contains a significant amount of general correspondence. One item of interest is the transition plan to move the oversight of the Journal from the University of Minnesota to Bethesda, Maryland. These files include correspondence, the ad hoc committee charged with undertaking the proposed move, the Conway Group files, and the actual proposed changes to the Journal, which included the new position of a Manuscript Processing Manager. The second sub-series, Newsletter, contains printed copies of the Biophysical Society Newsletter as well as pertinent correspondence and reports. Copies of the newsletter cover the time span 1958 – 2003 with very few gaps. This sub-series also contains a handful of copies of the Spectrum newsletter, which was published by the Committee for Professional Opportunities for Women (CPOW) of the Biophysical Society. The third sub-series, Publications Committee, consists of correspondence, reports, agendas, and minutes of said committee.
The fifth series, Affiliated Societies, contains files relating to organizations who had close ties to the Biophysical Society, and it is divided into two sub-series: the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (FASEB) and the International Union of Pure and Applied Biophysics (IUPAB). The first sub-series, FASEB, spans the years 1988 – 2002 and consists of correspondence, Board of Directors meeting files, reports, and files of the Summer Research Conference. The second sub-series, IUPAB, consists of a small amount of correspondence and miscellaneous material mostly from the 1990s.
The Biophysical Society was formally founded in March 1957 in Columbus, Ohio, after several years of planning and organizing. The organization process actually began in earnest in 1955 at two separate meetings called to address the need for a biophysical society. One conference, held in September 1955, met at Tufts College in connection with the American Physiological Society and was under the chairmanship of Dr. W. A. Selle of the Biophysics Department at the University of California, Los Angeles. The second meeting met at the Hartford House of the Yale Biophysics Department at Valhalla, New York. Both conferences agreed that a biophysical society was desirable; however the second meeting was more concerned with careers and training in biophysics. From these conferences, a committee, consisting of Drs. Cole, Hartline, Talbot and Curtis, was formed to advise the American Physiological Society. Approximately one hundred people next met in New York in January 1956 in the Hotel New Yorker in conjunction with the American Institute of Physics. Forty or fifty individuals were then formed into a steering committee with instructions to convene at the Atlantic City meeting of the Federation of Biological Societies on April 16, 1956. At the Federation meeting, the Committee of Four was elected, consisting of Samuel A. Talbot, Chairman, Kenneth S. Cole, Ernest C. Pollard and Otto H. Schmitt. At the Committee of Four’s First National Biophysics Conference held in Columbus, Ohio, March 4-6, 1957, the decision was made to organize a biophysical society, and a Temporary Council was elected. This Council made several proposals such as adopting the Constitution and Bylaws of the Society and preparing for the second meeting of the Biophysical Society. At this second meeting (the first regular national meeting) on February 6, 1958, in Cambridge, Massachusetts, all of the Temporary Council’s recommendations were accepted and the Biophysical Society elected its first set of officers with Robley C. Williams as the first president. From humble beginnings, the Society has grown into a professional organization with nearly 7,000 members in the United States and 45 countries.
In the early years, the Biophysical Society was guided and operated by volunteers who served as officers, members of Council, or on various committees. The Executive Board (originally named the Executive Council) consisted of four officers: President, President-Elect, Secretary, and Treasurer as well as the Past President and four members elected by the Council. Unlike the President and President-elect who serve for one year only, the Secretary and Treasurer serve staggered terms of four years. The Office of the Secretary, incorporating the position of Executive Director (also under various other titles over the years), is the hub of the Society coordinating its activities. Two of the secretaries, Margaret O. Dayhoff and Stephen H. White, also went on to serve as Society president after serving consecutive terms as Secretary. The Executive Director position, held by Emily Gray from 1972 – 1996, continues to be a vital part of the Secretary’s Office. The Executive Director acts as a liaison with the Officers, Executive Board and Council, and attends all meetings of the Executive Board and Council. The Executive Director is also responsible for maintaining membership lists and tracking dues payments. In addition, the Executive Director is in charge of the rest of the Society staff personnel, and is responsible for communication with other societies and the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (FASEB, which the Biophysical Society joined in 1991).
The position of the Executive Director shows the incredible growth of the Biophysical Society. The Society had grand ambitions from its inception, and began pursuing the publication of a society journal immediately upon its creation. In fact, many early members had been desirous of a journal for some time. Discussions began in earnest in 1956 because Academic Press wished to begin publishing a journal to be called “The Journal of Molecular Biology,” which it later decided would be a redundant publication. Early members of the Society began extensive correspondence with both Academic Press and Pergamon Press in hopes of finalizing a journal that the Society could publish. Both companies submitted proposals in 1957 to publish the Journal of Biophysics, and Academic Press was selected. However, several members, including officers on the Executive Board, expressed doubts as to the selection of Academic Press as a publisher. Therefore, the agreement was rescinded and correspondence was begun with the Rockefeller Institute Press (RIP). In August 1959, members selected an editorial board, and RIP began receiving manuscripts for publication in the summer of 1960. The first issue of the Biophysical Journal came out in September 1960, and volume one was completed in 1961. During these formative years, before the Journal could operate on a self-sustaining basis, RIP subsidized the Journal from its own resources. In 1989, the Society began to pursue the possibility of major changes at the Journal. In order to address more areas of interest, and to gain a wider readership, the Society set up an Ad Hoc Editorial Advisory Committee in 1989. Members of the committee submitted reports in November 1989, February 1990, and again in November 1991. After a meeting in Houston, the Society decided to make two significant changes to the Journal: the Journal would now be self-published by the Society (with guidance from Waverly Press), and every (non-student) member would automatically receive a subscription to the Journal with a modest increase in membership dues to compensate. These two changes, which included moving Journal operations from the University of Minnesota to Bethesda, were implemented in 1993. In 1996, the Society began pursuing an online version of the Journal, which is presently active. The Society also publishes a Newsletter.
The Biophysical Society has also been active in other areas such as biophysical meetings and group discussions. The Society established the National Lectures in 1969. The Society also sponsors meetings of sub-groups, which continually change over time to meet the changing needs of the biophysical community. The current sub-groups are Bioenergetics, Biological Fluorescence, Exocytosis/Endocytosis, Membrane Biophysics, Membrane Structure and Assembly, Molecular Biophysics, Motility, and Permeation/Transport. Each subgroup has their own chairperson, by-laws, and dues. The subgroups are designed to address more specific areas of interest. To address the wider interests of the biophysical community, the Society has held Annual Meetings since its inception in 1957. The Annual Meetings are designed to bring together the biophysical community in an informal atmosphere to discuss developments and have individual members present papers in specific areas to facilitate further discussion. The Annual Meetings serve to strengthen the Society as well by introducing new members to the community and promoting awareness of the Society and its activities.
The Society has also had a very active set of committees, which have only grown over the years. The Society has long been concerned with education and biophysics. The Educational Affairs Committee first met at the Annual Meeting in 1959. The committee first targeted college students interested in biophysics, but later also turned to younger students as well as post-doctoral students just launching into the career field. The Educational Affairs Committee sponsors workshops and symposia for students. The Society’s placement service also began immediately upon inception in 1957. The Society wanted to be able to advise its members about types of career opportunities open to research investigators. The Society facilitated communication between its members and organizations needing biophysicists. The Society uses questionnaires in order to better understand the needs of its members seeking placement. The Biophysical Society has also been concerned with women and minorities in biophysics. At the 1972 Annual Meeting the Committee on Professional Opportunities for Women (CPOW) was established. The CPOW has been very active over the years through its meetings in conjunction with the annual meetings, and through the Spectrum newsletter. The Minority Affairs Committee seeks to involve more minorities in the Society and promote career opportunities.
Due to the growth and duration of the Society, in June 1981, members were sent an annual mailing, which mentioned the new appointment of a Society archivist. The Executive Council, during the 1981 Denver meeting, elected Max Lauffer as the archivist. The purpose of electing an archivist was to assemble and preserve the history of the first 25 years of the Society. Members were asked to send memorabilia such as pictures, important correspondence about the work and organization of the Society, and newspaper clippings concerning meetings. Many members responded to this request, and to personal requests from Max Lauffer.
Organized into five series: Series I. Officers and Executive Committee, 1955-2002. Series II. Meetings, 1956-2002. Series III. Committees, 1956-1998. Series IV. Publications, 1956-2008. Series V. Affiliated Societies, 1964-2009.
Series I. Officers and Executive Committee
Legal Documents
Correspondence
Executive Board Meetings
Financial Documents
Administrative Files
Series II. Meetings
Annual
Miscellaneous Meetings and Conferences
Series III. Committees
Awards Committee
Educational Affairs Committee
Innovative Technology Fund Advisory Committee
Joint Steering Committee
Membership Committee
Nominating Committee
Miscellaneous Committees
Series IV. Publications
Biophysical Journal
Newsletter
Publications Committee
Series V. Affiliated Societies
Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (FASEB)
International Union of Pure and Applied Biophysics (IUPAB)
No restrictions.
Finding aid available.
The records in this collection were donated over a period of three years in five accessions and an additional accession eleven years later: SARCV 2003-03, SARCV 2003-01, SARCV 2002-02, SARCV 2001-03, SARCV 2000-08, SARCV 2014-05. The donations were approved by Ms. Rosalba Kampman and the materials transferred from the Society’s offices in Bethesda, MD.
Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology; International Union for Pure and Applied Biophysics; Biophysical journal; Biophysical Society Archives; Biophysics Societies, etc.
Biophysical Society. Accessed November 13, 2015.
Biophysical Journal Online. Accessed November 13, 2015.
Satin, L.S. "The Biophysical Society: A Short History." Biophysical Society. Accessed November 13, 2015.
- Series I. Officers and Executive Committee, 1955-2002; 11.25 linear feet
  Records of the original organizing committee and officers of the Society arranged into five Subseries: Association Legal Documents, Correspondence, Executive Board Meetings, Finances, and Administrative Files.
  - Subseries I.A. Association Legal Documents, 1957-1990; bulk 1958-1968; 5 folders (.25 linear feet)
    Articles of Incorporation, constitutions & by-laws, arranged in alphabetical order by type of document.
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Constitution & By-Laws: Formulation/Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Constitution & By-Laws: Drafts, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Constitution & By-Laws: Revision, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Constitution & By-Laws: Drafts, 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.B. Correspondence, 1955-1998; 121 folders (5.25 linear feet)
    General correspondence files of the association officers arranged in date order, followed by subject files arranged in alphabetical order by subject, followed by electronic mail correspondence arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
    - Correspondence/Organizing Committee, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence/Organizing Committee, Jan-March 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence/Organizing Committee, April 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence/Organizing Committee, May-July 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence/Organizing Committee, Sept.-Dec., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, January-July 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, August-December 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence/Executive Board, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence/General, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence/General, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, January-May 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, June-December 1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, January-May 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, June-September 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence, October-December 1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, January-May 1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence, June-December 1990 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, January-June 1991 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, July-September 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, October-December 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, January-March 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence/General, April-June 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence/General, July-September 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence/General, October-December 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, January-March 1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, April-June 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, July-October 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, April-June 1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, July-September 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, October-December 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, January-April 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, May-August 1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, September-December 1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, January 1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, February-September 1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, March 2005-February 2006 Part 1 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, March 2005-February 2006 Part 2 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, March 2005-February 2006 Part 3 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, March 2005-February 2006 Part 4 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, March 2006-February 2007 Part 1 of 5 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, March 2006-February 2007 Part 2 of 5 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, March 2006-February 2007 Part 3 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, March 2006-February 2007 Part 4 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, March 2006-February 2007 Part 5 of 5 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, March 2008-February 2009 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, March 2009-February 2010 Part 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, March 2009-February 2010 Part 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, March 2009-February 2010 Part 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence/Accountant, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence/Administrative Director, 1988-89 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence/Administrative Director, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence/Administrative Director, 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence/Awards, 1992, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence/Biomolecular Database/Politics, December 1993-February 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence/Biomedical Database Politics, April-May 1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence/Biophysical Discussion, Sixth, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)